<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Idea Conservatory</title>
    <description>Ideas, Objects, Creativity</description>
    <link>https://ideaconservatory.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ideaconservatory.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2020 17:42:12 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2020 17:42:12 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>

    
      <item>
        <title>A fundamental way to reason about technology</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chances were, that the first image that came into your mind after reading that word, was that of a building. Another fun fact – pieces of code, of instructions that make up software are called ‘Builds’! Developers, Routes, Storage, Architects, Stacks, the more you understand the glossary of the digital world you soon realize, that despite being so abstract – it is actually a mirror of our physical world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Being human in the digital world is about building a digital world for humans. - Andrew Keen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern research in physics, has revealed that underneath the quantum level lies another level, a level from which space and time (physical reality) both emerge (the wavefunction) - and that is  at the level of ‘information’. Perhaps this is why the dawn of the information age, propelled our world to exponential heights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here is the question, ‘what made it so transformational?’ A clue to begin the search for this answer, lies in what happened when humans began to, not just collect information, but arrange and organize it effectively towards a single goal - To transform the environment that surrounded them and bend it to their will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-transformation-of-ones-environment&quot;&gt;The Transformation of one’s environment&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a pattern that manifests itself throughout human history as we sought to transform our environment. The Model-View-Controller. A horse drawn cart is replaced by a diesel engine because humans began to think of information related to the model (transportation systems) as separate from the view (horse or engine) and the controller (coachman or driver).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1562657551-5ca50b25d3da?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;ixid=eyJhcHBfaWQiOjEyMDd9&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=1355&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very effective way to reason about and articulate problems that address specific concerns, without having to dream up a completely new idea. For example, incremental improvements can be done by improving the Controller. Innovation can be achieved by changing the View. And radical re-thinking can be achieved by changing the Model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get back to the horse and cart situation — better transportation time can be achieved by getting a better coachmen (controller); unthinkably better times can be achieved by replacing the horse with an engine (view); and entire societies are transformed with the ability to make a car appear by pressing two buttons in the palm of your hand. (the model).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1554672408-730436b60dde?ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;ixid=eyJhcHBfaWQiOjEyMDd9&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=667&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-another-example-this-time-from-banking&quot;&gt;Using another example, this time from banking:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving the controller (logical &amp;amp; algorithmic efficiency) may result in a better transaction speeds;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving the view will change the user experience (i.e. banking experience — branch to web to mobile);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving the model (i.e. crypto-currency) seeks to radically transform society.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/27.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;
Let us now use this image to understand how the digital world works, from a web development perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Drawings help people to work out intricate relationships between parts - Christopher Alexander&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;model-view-controller-web-development&quot;&gt;Model-View-Controller: Web development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;view&quot;&gt;View&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/28.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the View, as it resides on the upper most part of the information ‘Stack’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view, as its name implies refers to what is ‘rendered’ on your screen. The word rendered is used because what you see, right from the colors, fonts, animations, styles, the layout every single icon has instructions written in code. The people who do this are, ‘Front End Developers’, as the name suggests – working on what is seen and experienced – the front end. As we have architects for buildings, we have ‘User Interface Designers’ who create the interfaces.
The tools and languages used to create views:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HTML – Hypertext Markup Language: Is like an information templating system to plan information layouts on the screen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CSS – Cascading Style Sheets: These are instruction templates that deal with the styling of the HTML&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JavaScript – Also referred to as JS, They integrate instructions and enable interactivity with the information presented using HTML/CSS. They can listen to events, that is - if a mouse has clicked a part of the page, if you have swiped left, or if you have filtered a data list for visualization. All the interactivity you have experienced in the modern web is thanks to JavaScript.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;model&quot;&gt;Model&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model is probably the hardest to define. Can the model be a scaffold — like a view-model — on which actual data gets mounted? Now we are thinking of modelling visual representations. Can a model contain business logic? What if you had an Account model and it had associated maintenance fee, interests rate, and rules for how they are applied — could you now query the model to get insight on how much money I will have after 5 years? The Model is essentially, structured data, arranged as records - like the ones you find on a spreadsheet. The model only represents the data, it does nothing else. It does not depend on the controller or the view. The people who do this are called ‘Backend Developers’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many tools used to create and store models, for our scope in this article I shall focus on databases, in particular – relational databases and non-relational databases.\&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Relational Databases (RDBMS – Relational Database Management System): These are similar to what you see on excel. They store data in columns and rows - tables. A collection of tables make a schema. A number of schemas create a database. Relational databases are robust, and are used when the data is structured. Some of the popular relational databases are: MySQL, PostgreSQL, SAPHANA,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Non-Relational Databases: These are more recent, and are an innovative way of storing data. Here data isn’t stored in a tabular form. You can think of it as Data stored as documents on a bookshelf. Another way to look at it would be like your folder on the PC. You can have audiofiles, videofiles, slides and documents all in one folder irrespective of the file type. It follows similar fashion here. With more and more businesses getting into big data, non relational databases make it easy to store, retrieve and manipulate data. Some of the popular non relational databases are: MongoDB, Cassandra, Redis, Neo4j&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;controller&quot;&gt;Controller&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/30.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;
The controller is easier to explain. The controller ties the model to the view. It is the layer sandwiched between the view and the model. It contains all the logic as well as the routes to the data model in the backend. Information architects and User Experience designers play a critical role in providing inputs to those that design routes and controllers that fetch data from the backend and present them in the view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tying-it-all-together-from-the-physical-world&quot;&gt;Tying it all together from the physical world&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://strunkmarketing.com/bitmoto/ford/images/custom/ford-techs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s reinforce what we have learnt so far by going back in time to consider a situation without digital technology. Imagine a store clerk at an auto parts warehouse. A customer comes in and says he wants to buy brake pads for a 1992 Honda Civic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The clerk looks up where that part is stored in the warehouse and brings it to the customer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The customer inspects it and then moves to the other clerk at the cash register to purchase the part.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The second clerk inspects the part and asks for a specific amount of money to complete the transaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first scenario — looking up the part — the view was the physical part, the model was the part as a component of the warehouse inventory. In the second scenario the model was still the part as a component of the warehouse inventory, but the view was the price. In this contrived scenario we have two controllers — the clerk that finds the part based on some query parameters, and the clerk, that given a part, requests some money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;interpretation-into-the-digital-world&quot;&gt;Interpretation into the digital world&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/31.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bringing it back to the regular web application this process becomes easily translatable. On a landing page we look for a part. Our initial view is that of a search field that provides an interface to find something we are looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As we click “Search” this information is passed to a controller that then finds the model that matches, ties it to view and returns it back to the user. The user looks at the view of the search results — essentially one or more models — and makes a choice.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A different controller then takes the model(s) and renders a new view that now will show the price, the sales tax, shipping information etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In short, we have many controllers tying models to different views. Each view arises out of the customer needs identified in the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-oppurtunity-for-transformation&quot;&gt;The oppurtunity for transformation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us conclude by tying some philosophical musings with the concrete ideas behind the model-view-controller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are a looking for gradual improvement, or improvement in performance - look at changing the Controller.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are looking for innovation, look at changing or presenting a different View.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are looking for Radical Transformation look at changing the Model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most techies may look at the Model-View-Controller as a mere pattern or an architecture, but it has a more powerful purpose. It provides a fundamental way to reason about technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next session we are going to understand the process of building. Say you wanted to build an app. How would you go about doing it? Where and how would you start? What are the steps and resources involved and how does anthropology, design, engineering and digital innovation fit into all this. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>13 Mar 2020</pubDate>
        <link>https://ideaconservatory.org/2020/03/13/a-fundamental-way-to-reason-about-technology/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ideaconservatory.org/2020/03/13/a-fundamental-way-to-reason-about-technology/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Digital Glossary</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A handpicked compilation to the digital terms commonly used today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a&quot;&gt;A&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accessibility&quot;&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accessibility is the process of making web content accessible to people with disabilities such as
those who are visually impaired, hearing-impaired, colour blind people, or anyone else who cannot for whatever reason, use a computer in a conventional manner. A website with poor accessibility will be difficult for these people to use. Accessibility is particularly important for sites providing information to those with disabilities such as those in the healthcare sector and government departments. Accessibility is an important aspect to consider when designing any site. Guidelines for the various levels of accessibility are set by industry bodies, such as the W3C WAI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ajax&quot;&gt;AJAX&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Asynchronous JavaScript and XML. AJAX is typically used for creating dynamic web applications and allows for asynchronous data retrieval – content updating without the web page having to reload. The JavaScript on any given page handles most of the basic functions of the application, making it perform more like a desktop program instead of a web-based one. A good example of AJAX in action is Google Maps – which allows the visitor to scroll around a map without the browser refreshing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anchor-text&quot;&gt;Anchor Text&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anchor text usually gives the user relevant descriptive or contextual information about the content of the link’s destination. The anchor text above in bold – what the visitor will see on a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;api-application-programming-interface&quot;&gt;API (Application Programming Interface)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way computer programs share data and functionality with other computer programs. APIs are an increasingly critical part of the Internet’s interconnection. Many say that the future of the Internet lies in APIs because they help distribute and combine content. On the Web, APIs are generally special URLs that give back machine-readable data, in formats like JSON or XML, rather than human-readable data, which is usually HTML. Facebook, Twitter and Google Maps all have APIs that allow other websites or computer programs to use their underlying tools. The New York Times and NPR have also released APIs that allow other programs to draw on archives of movie reviews, restaurant reviews and articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;android&quot;&gt;Android&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually used in the context of Android phone, Android is a free and open source operating system developed by Google that powers a variety of mobile phones from different manufacturers and carriers. It is a rival of the iPhone platform. In contrast to Apple’s tightly controlled architecture and App Store, Android allows users to install apps from the Android Market and from other channels, such as directly from a developer’s website — which allows for X-rated content, for example. Some well-known Android phones are the Nexus One, the Motorola Droid and HTC Evo. Expect to see competitors to the iPad running a version of Android.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;app&quot;&gt;App&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short for application, a program that runs inside another service. Many mobile phones allow apps to be downloaded, leading to a burgeoning economy for modestly priced software. Can also refer to a program or tool that can be used within a website. Apps generally are built using software toolkits provided by the underlying service, whether it is iPhone or Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;algorithm&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A set of instructions or procedures used in order to accomplish a task, such as creating search
results in Google. In the context of search, algorithms are used to provide the most relevant results first based on those instructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;atom&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A syndication format for machine-readable web feeds that is usually accessible via a URL. While it was created as an alternative to RSS (Real Simple Syndication) to improve upon RSS’s deficiencies (such as ambiguities), it still is secondary to RSS. (See also, RSS)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ama&quot;&gt;AMA&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask me anything. A style of Reddit post, in which the poster opens themselves up to questions and answers them in the comments, usually done in real-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;analytics&quot;&gt;Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring, analysing and interpreting activity and interactions on and across social media
platforms. It is a powerful tool for marketers, enabling them to see how they are performing against Social Media Objectives and where they can improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;avatar&quot;&gt;Avatar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A picture or a graphic that represents you or your company online. Also commonly known as a
Profile Picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;atl&quot;&gt;ATL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above the line ads include any which focus on general media such as TV, cinema, radio, print and the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audience-segment&quot;&gt;Audience segment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A group of users with similar traits or characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audience-targeting&quot;&gt;Audience targeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Targeting of specific audience segments, such as an age demographic. Audience segments can be defined in OpenX or in an external data management platform (DMP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audit-trail&quot;&gt;Audit trail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logging of any changes to data (creation, modification, or deletion) to allow a system admin user to review all historical changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;b&quot;&gt;B&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;back-end&quot;&gt;Back End&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The back end of a website is the part hidden from view of regular website visitors. The back end generally includes the information structure, applications, and the CMS controlling content on the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;backlink&quot;&gt;Backlink&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backlinks are links from other websites back to yours. They are sometimes also referred to as
“trackbacks” (especially on blogs). Backlinks have a huge impact on your sites search rankings. Lots of backlinks from high-ranking sites can greatly improve your search engine results, especially if those links use keywords in their anchor text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bad-neighbourhood&quot;&gt;Bad Neighbourhood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A “bad neighbourhood” refers to the server where your site is hosted. A site hosted on a server that hosts other sites that spam or use black-hat SEO practices can end up penalised by search engines solely because of their proximity to those sites. Linking to sites in bad neighbourhoods can also have a negative effect on your search rankings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bandwidth&quot;&gt;Bandwidth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandwidth can refer to two different things: the rate at which data can be transferred, or the total amount of data allowed to be transferred from a web host during a given month (or other hosting service term) before overage charges are applied. It is generally referred to in term of bits-per-second (bps), kilobits per second (kbs), or other metric measurements. Lower bandwidth internet connections such as dial-up mean data loads slower than with high bandwidth connections such as broadband.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;below-the-fold&quot;&gt;Below the Fold&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This term is a carry-over from newspaper publishing days. In newspaper terms, “below the fold” means content was on the bottom half of the page below the physical fold in the paper. In web design terms, “below the fold” refers to the content that is going to appear off of the bottom of the screen for the average website visitor in their browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bounce-rate&quot;&gt;Bounce Rate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Website bounce rate is the number, or percentage of people who leave the site from the same page they entered, without clicking through to any other pages. This can be a good indicator of how good the navigation on the website is, as well as an indicator of the quality of the content on the website. Generally, a high bounce rate indicates a poor page design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breadcrumb&quot;&gt;Breadcrumb&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breadcrumbs are the navigational elements that generally appear near the top of a given web page that show you the pages and subpages that appear before the page you’re on. For example, on a blog, the breadcrumb might look something like: Home &amp;gt; Category &amp;gt; Year &amp;gt; Month &amp;gt; Post, or maybe a lot simpler. The term ‘breadcrumb’ comes from the fairy tale “Hansel and Gretel.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;browser&quot;&gt;Browser&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Browser refers to the program a website visitor is using to view the website. Examples include
Safari, Firefox, Google Chrome, Opera, and Internet Explorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blog&quot;&gt;Blog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A personal or company website or web page on which an individual or group of individuals post informal articles, record opinions or share links, videos or imagery, on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blogger-outreach&quot;&gt;Blogger Outreach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process by which you ‘reach out’ to other bloggers within your industry or category. Blogger outreach involves contacting individual bloggers and asking them if they are interested in either hosting content you’ve created for them or in writing content and mentioning or linking to your website or brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bloggersphere-or-blogosphere&quot;&gt;Bloggersphere or Blogosphere&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A term to refer to all known blogs on the internet and their interconnections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;banner&quot;&gt;Banner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an ad that appears on a web page which is typically hyperlinked to an advertiser’s website. Banners can be images (GIF, JPEG, PNG), JavaScript programs or multimedia objects (Flash, Java, Shockwave etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;c&quot;&gt;C&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;call-to-action&quot;&gt;Call to Action&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A specific action or request that you hope a person will take, such as “”Call For a Free Consultation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cachecaching&quot;&gt;Cache/Caching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cached files are those that are saved or copied (downloaded) by a web browser so that the next time that user visits the site, the page loads faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cascading-style-sheets-css&quot;&gt;Cascading Style Sheets (CSS)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also referred to simply as CSS, Cascading Style Sheets are used to define the look and feel of a website outside of the actual HTML of the site. In recent years, CSS has replaced tables and other HTML-based methods for formatting and laying out websites. The benefits of using CSS are many, but some of the most important are the simplification of a site’s HTML files, which can actually increase search engine rankings and the ability to completely change the style of a site by changing just one file without having to make changes to content. The latest version is CSS3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cgi&quot;&gt;CGI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Common Gateway Interface (CGI) is a standard protocol for interfacing external application software with an information server, commonly a web server. CGI usually comes in the form of a script, which is called to perform a particular function on a website. CGI scripts are usually written in a programming language called PERL&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;client-side&quot;&gt;Client-Side&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Client-side refers to scripts that are run in a visitor’s browser, instead of on a web server – as in server-side scripts. Client-side scripts are generally faster to interact with, though they can take longer to load initially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;civic-media&quot;&gt;civic media&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An umbrella term describing media technologies that create a strong sense of engagement among residents through news and information. It is often used as a contrast to “citizen journalism” because it also encompasses mapping, wikis, and databases. MIT has a Center for Future Civic Media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cloud-computing&quot;&gt;cloud computing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An increasingly popular computing model in which information and software are provided on
demand from over the Internet rather than staying on local computers. Cloud computing is
appealing because companies can reduce the amount they spend on their own computer servers and software but can also quickly and easily expand as the company grows. Examples of cloud computing applications include Google Docs and Yahoo Mail. Amazon offers two cloud computing services: EC2, which many start-ups now use as a cheap way to launch their products, and S3, an online storage system many companies use for cheap storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-management-system-cms&quot;&gt;Content Management System (CMS)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also known as a CMS, the Content Management System is a backend tool for managing the content of a website. The CMS separates the core content (text, images, video) from the design and functionality of the site. Using a CMS generally, makes it easier to change the design or function of a site independently of the website content. It will often make it easier for administrators who aren’t web developers, to add content to a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;Comment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In web design terms, a comment is a bit of information contained in the HTML or XHTML of a web page, which is ignored by the browser. Comments are used to identify different parts of the file and as reference notes. Good commenting makes it much easier for a web designer to make changes to the site, as it clearly defines which parts of the code perform what functions. There are different comment formats for different programming and markup languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cpa-cost-per-action&quot;&gt;CPA (Cost Per Action)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pricing model in which the advertiser is charged for an ad based on how many users take a
specific, pre-defined action–such as buying a product from an online store–based on viewing an ad. This is the “gold standard” for advertisers because it most directly matches the cost of an ad to its effectiveness. However, it’s not commonly used since it’s extremely difficult to measure: it is often unclear when or how to attribute an action to a specific ad. (Also sometimes referred to as Cost Per Acquisition.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cpc-cost-per-click&quot;&gt;CPC (Cost Per Click)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pricing model in which the advertiser is charged for an ad based on how many users click it. This is a common model for “search advertising” (the all-text ads associated with search results) and with text ads in general. CPC is well-suited for “directed” advertising, intended to prompt an immediate response because a user’s clicking on an ad shows engagement with it. Google AdWords is generally priced on a CPC basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cpm-cost-per-mille&quot;&gt;CPM (Cost Per Mille)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost per one thousand (often views). Much of online advertising — particularly display advertising — is priced on a CPM basis. (Mille = Latin for one thousand; we use “K” for “kilo” almost everywhere else in tech, but “M” for “mille” here, which causes some confusion.) CPM is well suited for “brand” or “awareness” advertising, in which the primary purpose of the ad is not necessarily to prompt an immediate response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creative-commons&quot;&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A flexible set of copyright licenses that allow content creators to specify which rights they reserve and which they waive regarding their work that is supposed to codify collaborative spirit of the Internet. There are six main Creative Commons licenses based on four conditions that creators can choose to apply: Attribution, Share Alike, Non-Commercial, and No Derivative Works. The least restrictive of the licenses is Attribution, which grants anyone, from an individual to a large company, the right to distribute, display, or otherwise make use of the work so long as the creator is credited. The most restrictive is Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives, which grants only redistribution. First released in December 2002 by the nonprofit Creative Commons organization, which was inspired by the open source GNU GPL license, the licenses are now used on an estimated 130 million works worldwide. The glossary you are reading is released under a Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike license in an effort to encourage wide distribution and contribution. (Also see open source)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cloud-computing-1&quot;&gt;Cloud Computing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A type of computing where resources are retrieved from the internet through web-based tools and applications, rather than being stored on local servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community-manager&quot;&gt;Community Manager&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsible for building, growing and managing online communities around a brand, cause or topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-marketing&quot;&gt;Content Marketing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A marketing technique of creating and distributing relevant and valuable online content to attract, acquire, and engage a clearly defined target audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-strategy&quot;&gt;Content Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The planning and development for the creation, delivery, and governance of online, shareable content. A content strategy should outline what social channels to use, what types of content are to be shared via what channels, and a schedule of content production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conversion&quot;&gt;Conversion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A conversion is the completion of a goal by an end user of a website – having gone through a series of steps to reach that goal. A goal can be defined as anything, ranging from the user completing a registration form or survey, downloading a file or purchasing something. Conversion rate is a good measure of the performance of a website and will often be the benchmark used when trying to improve the efficiency of a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;css-framework&quot;&gt;CSS Framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A CSS framework is a collection of CSS files used as the starting point to make XHTML and CSS websites quickly and painlessly. They usually contain CSS styles for typography and layout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;csv-comma-separated-values&quot;&gt;CSV (Comma-Separated Values)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extremely simple data format which stores information in a text file. CSV is popular precisely because it can be easily read by many different applications, including spreadsheets, word processors, programming text editors and web browsers. Thus it is a common way for people, including governments, to make their data available. Each row of data is represented by a line of text. Each column is delimited/separated by a comma (,). To prevent confusion about commas in the data, the terms are often surrounded by double quotes (“). Many applications support the use of alternative column delimiters (the pipe character, |, is popular). Example below:
“Name”,”Address”,”email”
“Jack”,”1 Main St., Town, NY”,”jack@hill.com”
“Jill”,”2 Elm St., City, CA”,jill@hill.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;d&quot;&gt;D&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-visualization&quot;&gt;Data visualization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A growing area of content creation in which information is represented graphically and often
interactively. This can be used for subjects as diverse as an analysis of a speech by the president and the popularity of baby names over time. While it has deep roots in academia, data visualization has begun to emerge on content sites as a way to handle the masses of data that are being made public, often by government. There are many tools for data visualizations, including Seattle-based Tableau and IBM’s Many Eyes. Data visualization should 1) tell a story, 2) allow users to ask their own questions and 3) start conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;document-oriented-database&quot;&gt;Document-oriented database&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An increasingly popular type of database. In contrast to relational databases, which rigidly require information to be stored in pre-defined tables, document-oriented databases are more free-flowing and flexible. This is important when you don’t know what is going to be thrown at you. Documentoriented databases retrieve information more quickly but store it less efficiently. The same document-oriented database might let you store the information for an article (headline, byline, data, content, miscellaneous) or for a photo (file, photographer, date, cutline). MongoDB is a popular open source document-oriented database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drupal&quot;&gt;Drupal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A popular content management system known for a vibrant open-source community that creates diverse and robust extensions. Drupal is very powerful, but it is somewhat difficult to use for simple tasks when compared to WordPress. Drupal provides options to create a static website, a multiuser blog, an Internet forum or a community website for user-generated content. It is written in PHP and distributed under the GPL open source license. Whitehouse.gov uses Drupal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;django&quot;&gt;Django&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A web framework that is popular among news and information sites, in part due to its origin at Lawrence Journal-World in Kansas. It is written in Python, a sophisticated dynamic language. Major projects built in Django include Disqus, Everyblock.com and TheOnion.com. News applications teams, including those at the Chicago Tribune and Los Angeles Times, use the framework to present large data sets online in easily accessible ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deprecated&quot;&gt;Deprecated&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deprecated code is code that is no longer included in the language specifications. Generally, this happens because it is replaced with more accessible or efficient alternatives. This happens when a new version of a programming language or framework is released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dhtml&quot;&gt;DHTML&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Dynamic HyperText Markup Language. DHTML fuses XHTML (or any other markup language), the DOM, JavaScript (or other scripts), and CSS (or other presentation definition languages) to create interactive web content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dns&quot;&gt;DNS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for ‘Domain Name Service’ or alternately ‘Domain Name System’, or ‘Domain Name Server’. The DNS converts IP addresses into domain names. DNS servers are provided with the IP address of your web server when you assign your domain name to those servers. In turn, when someone types your domain name into their web browser the DNS servers translate the domain name to the IP address and point the browser to the correct web server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;doctype&quot;&gt;Doctype&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The doctype declaration specifies which version of HTML is used in a document. It has a direct effect on whether your HTML will validate or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dom-the&quot;&gt;DOM, The&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Document Object Model. It is a language-independent, cross-platform convention for representing objects in XML, XHTML, and HTML documents. Rules for interacting with and programming the DOM are specified in the DOM API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;domain&quot;&gt;Domain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The domain is the name by which a website is identified. The domain is associated with an IP address. Domains can be purchased with any combination of letters, hyphens (-), and numbers (though it can’t start with a hyphen). Depending on the extension (.com, .net, .org, etc.), a domain can be anywhere up to 26 to 63 characters long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;domain-authority&quot;&gt;Domain Authority&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a scale from 1-100 that search engines use to determine how authoritative a company’s website is, 1 being the lowest rank and 100 being the highest. The higher your domain authority the more Search Engines trust you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dtd&quot;&gt;DTD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Document Type Definition. DTD is one of several SGML and XML schema languages. It provides a list of the attributes, comments, elements, entities, and notes in a document along with their relationships to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;e&quot;&gt;E&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;earned-media&quot;&gt;Earned Media&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Word of mouth mentions of your company, generated on a person to person basis EC2
A computing power rental system by Amazon that has become popular among technology
companies because it is much cheaper than maintaining your own computer servers. Users can host their applications on EC2 and pay depending on usage. EC2 is an example of cloud computing. (Also see cloud computing)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;e-commerce&quot;&gt;E-Commerce&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short for Electronic Commerce, E-Commerce is the process of buying and selling of goods online through websites. Products sold through e-commerce can be physical products that require shipping, or digital products delivered electronically such as program and document downloads, license keys and music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;elastic-layout&quot;&gt;Elastic Layout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An elastic layout is one that uses percentage and em for defining page width, paired with a max width style to allow the layout of the website to stretch when font sizes are changed. The ability to flex to accommodate the browser width and visitor’s font preferences is where the name ‘elastic’ comes from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;element&quot;&gt;Element&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In XML, an element is the central building block of any document. Individual elements can contain text, other elements, or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;em&quot;&gt;Em&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em is a unit of measurement for sizing fonts and other elements within a web page relative to the parent element of the item. A 1em font is equal to the point size for the font already defined in the parent element. For example, 2em would be twice the current size, .5em would be half the current size and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;embedded-style&quot;&gt;Embedded Style&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An embedded style is a CSS style written into the head of an XHTML document. t only affects the elements on that page, instead of site-wide as a separate CSS file does. Style in an embedded style sheet will override styles from the linked CSS file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;engagement&quot;&gt;Engagement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engagement or Social Engagement refers to the amount of participation in an online community. Retweets, comments, and Likes are all forms of social engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ex&quot;&gt;Ex&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ex is a measurement for font height or size relative to the height of a lowercase “x” in that font
family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;extensible-markup-language&quot;&gt;Extensible Markup Language&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise known as XML. XML is a markup language used for writing custom markup languages. In other words, XML describes how to write new languages. It is sometimes referred to as a “meta” language because of this. It also serves as a basic syntax that allows different kinds of computers and applications to share information without having to go through multiple conversion layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;external-style-sheet&quot;&gt;External Style Sheet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is CSS that is stored in an external document. The biggest advantage to using an external style sheet is that it can be linked to by multiple HTML/XHTML files, meaning that changes made to the style sheet will affect all the pages linked to it, rather than having to change each page individually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;event-tracking&quot;&gt;Event Tracking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code on web pages that allows Google Analytics to track and measure events on web pages, such as clicks or downloads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goal-tracking&quot;&gt;Goal Tracking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code on web pages that allows Google Analytics to track when certain tasks are completed, such as a download.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;f&quot;&gt;F&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;facebook-connect&quot;&gt;Facebook Connect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A technology from Facebook that allows a reader to log into a third-party website with their
Facebook account, rather than creating a new profile for that website. Facebook Connect, which is an API, also allows the third parties to pull certain data from the user’s profile, such as his or her name and age. In turn, the reader’s activities on the website can also be displayed on her or his Facebook profile. Launched in 2007, Facebook Connect was one of the first examples of Facebook extending itself into a platform for the entire Web. (Also see OAuth, Open ID)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;facebook&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook is a social utility that connects people with friends and others who work, study and live around them. People use Facebook to connect and share content with friends and associates. Facebook is now the largest social network on the internet, with more than 400 million active users, half of whom log on to Facebook in any given day. People spend over 500 billion minutes per month on Facebook&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;favicon&quot;&gt;Favicon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Favicons are tiny (generally 16×16 pixels, though some are 32×32 pixels), customizable icons
displayed in the web address bar in most browsers next to the web address. They’re either 8-bit or 24-bit in color depth and are saved in either .ico, .gif or .png file formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;facebook-fan-page&quot;&gt;Facebook fan page&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Facebook profile for a specific person, product, company or organization, usually administered by official representatives. This is different from a Facebook personal page, which must be owned by an individual, and different from a Facebook community page, which is built around an interest not related to a brand, such as “cooking.” It is also different from a Facebook group. Fan pages can gather thousands or millions of fans through “likes,” and official posts by the page administrator generally go into the fans’ news streams. Once a page has more than 25 fans, it can claim a short form URL, such as facebook.com/nytimes or facebook.com/wikileaks. Facebook community and fan pages are strong players in ongoing efforts to bring content to people where they already are, instead of requiring them to come to the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;facebook-group&quot;&gt;Facebook group&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook groups are analogous to offline clubs. Unlike Facebook fan pages, groups do not have to be administered by official representatives. In addition, the activity posted in groups does not get pushed into users’ feeds. But as long as it has fewer than 5,000 members, Facebook groups are allowed to mass-message all their members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;facebook-personal-page&quot;&gt;Facebook personal page&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A profile page tied to a single individual. What information is controlled (in theory) by the individual. However, because there is a 5,000-person limit to friends, some celebrities have fan pages instead. As of 2009, individuals can choose a username, which makes their page available at facebook.com/username.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flash&quot;&gt;Flash&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proprietary platform owned by Adobe Systems that allows for drag-and-drop animations, program interactivity, and dynamic displays for the Web. The language used, ActionScript, is owned by Adobe; this contrasts with many other popular programming languages that are open source. Creators must use Adobe’s Creative Suite products and web surfers must install a Flash plug-in for their browser. Many claim that Flash players are unstable and inefficient, slowing down web pages and crashing operating systems. Apple has not allowed Adobe to create a Flash player for the iPhone operating system, which has created a feud between the two companies. HTML5 is emerging as an open alternative to Flash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;framework&quot;&gt;Framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A software package that makes writing programs easier by providing all the “plumbing” for a
particular type of task (like writing a web app), allowing programmers to just “fill in the blanks” with their own project-specific needs. For instance, Web development frameworks like Ruby on Rails (written in Ruby, meaning programmers use Ruby to do the “fill in the blanks” tasks) and Django (written in Python), have easy-to-use, built-in support for common web development tasks, such as reading and writing to a database, writing content in html, and so forth. Watch Django and Ruby creators discuss the merits of their frameworks on DjangoProject.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;facetime&quot;&gt;Facetime&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A free video chat and VOIP software application developed by Apple to run on all devices running iOS, the Apple operating system found on iPhones, iPads, and computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flickr&quot;&gt;Flickr&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An image and video hosting website popular with bloggers and owned by Yahoo!
Forums An online discussion site where registered users can hold conversations in the form of posted messages, or threads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;foursquare&quot;&gt;Foursquare&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foursquare is a geo-social network where users can “check-in” to places they are visiting, leave tips, add reviews and post pictures. Geo-social works by combining a traditional social networking model of registered users who connect with one another, to GPS (Global Positioning Satellite) technology. By connecting these two models, users don’t just get updates, they also get information about where the updates were made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fixed-width-layout&quot;&gt;Fixed Width Layout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fixed width web page layout has a set width, usually defined in pixels. The width stays the same regardless of screen resolution, monitor size, or browser window size. It allows for minute adjustments to be made to a design that will stay consistent across browsers. Designers have more control over exactly how a site will appear across platforms with this type of layout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flash-1&quot;&gt;Flash&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adobe Flash is a technology that enables websites to display vector-based animation. More recently, Flash has become a powerful tool for creating web-based applications. Files created in Flash can now be distributed as stand-alone desktop applications by using another technology – Adobe Air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focal-point&quot;&gt;Focal Point&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focal point of a website is the spot on a web page that the eye is naturally drawn to. This could be an image, a banner, text, Flash content, or just about anything else. It is important to ensure that the focal point is the most important part of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;font-family&quot;&gt;Font Family&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A font family is a group designation for defining the typefaces used in CSS documents. The font family tag generally lists multiple fonts to be used, and usually ends with the generic font category such as “serif” or “sans-serif”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;font-style&quot;&gt;Font Style&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In CSS, the font style refers solely to whether a font is italic or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;font-weight&quot;&gt;Font Weight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The font weight refers to how thick or thin (bold or light) a font looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;front-end&quot;&gt;Front-End&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front-end is the opposite of the back-end. It is all the components of a website that a visitor to the site can physically see such as pages, images, and other content. More specifically, it is the interface that visitors use to access the website content. It is also sometimes referred to as the User Interface (UI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;g&quot;&gt;G&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;google&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World’s largest Internet search engine, indexing literally billions of web pages. In May 2010, 30.7m people in the UK searched on Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;google-analytics&quot;&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Google tool used to measure data about your website’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;google-adsense&quot;&gt;Google AdSense&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google’s online advertising network that allows content publishers to embed a piece of code to
display Google ads on their sites. The ads are selected based on the content of the page. Ad revenue is split between Google and the publisher in an undisclosed proportion, generally believed to be twothirds to the publisher. (Note: ads on Google’s own sites are covered by Google AdWords, not AdSense.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;google-adwords&quot;&gt;Google AdWords&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google’s text-based flagship advertising product, which provides the lion’s share of the company revenue. Ads are displayed on Google’s own sites based on search terms that users type in, and advertisers pay only when the users click on them. The search terms, called keywords, are purchased by advertisers; availability of a given keyword is based in part on an auction system, and in part on the responsiveness of the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;graceful-degradation&quot;&gt;Graceful Degradation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graceful degradation refers to the ability for a website to have elements that may take advantage of the capabilities of newer browsers, but done in a way which allows users with older browsers to still view the site in a manner that at least allows them access to basic content. It also applies to making sure that if one small portion of your site does not work in someone’s browser, it does not cause the site to error or crash in their browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;graphical-user-interface&quot;&gt;Graphical User Interface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also referred to by its acronym: GUI. A graphical user interface uses an input device such as a mouse and gives visual representations of how the user is able to interact with a web application. In other words, a GUI is all of the front-end stuff you see on a web application. The purpose of a GUI is to allow you to interact with a web application without having to enter code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;geolocationgeotagging&quot;&gt;Geolocation/Geotagging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geolocation is the process of finding, determining and providing the exact location of a computer or networking device. It enables the use of a variety of location-based apps, such as Foursquare, Facebook, Google Maps, Urbanspoon and RunKeeper. It is being used by bricks and mortar shops, such as retail spaces and restaurants, to increase online/offline social engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;google-1&quot;&gt;Google+&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A social network owned and operated by Google. Users can post stories, share videos and pictures, organise friends into circles, join communities and chat to other users. Your Google+ account syncs up with all other Google accounts you may have; Gmail, YouTube, etc. It is the second largest social networking site in the world, after Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;google-authorship&quot;&gt;Google Authorship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A way of linking the content you create, on any website, with your Google+ profile. When you have correctly set-up Google Authorship, your profile picture will appear in Google search results beside any written content you publish online. As Google’s search algorithm favours content from thought leaders and experts, using Google Authorship is a way to boost your ranking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;google-hangouts&quot;&gt;Google Hangouts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An instant messaging and video chat platform developed by Google, that works across all computers and both Android and Apple phones and tablets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;h&quot;&gt;H&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hashtag&quot;&gt;Hashtag&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A word or unspaced phrase prefixed with the # symbol. Commonly used on social networking sites such as Twitter, Google+ and Instagram. Appending a hashtag to a post both helps to give that message context and groups it with other messages about that same topic or event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hootsuite&quot;&gt;Hootsuite&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A social media management platform that allows users and brand managers to update, post, schedule and respond via multiple social media platforms, including; for Facebook, Twitter, LinkedIn, Google+, and WordPress. Hootsuite operates on a freemium model with products built for casual and enterprise users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hexadecimal&quot;&gt;Hexadecimal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also referred to a “hex” numbers, they are a base-16 numbering system used to define colors
online. Hex numbers include the numerals 0-9 and letters A-F. Hexadecimal numbers are written in three sets of hex pairs. Because screen colours are Red, Green and Blue the first pair defines the Red hue, the second pair defines the Green hue, and the third pair defines the Blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hit&quot;&gt;Hit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to popular belief, a hit does not represent a single visitor to a website. A hit is actually a request for a single file from your web server. This means one page can actually generate multiple hits, as each page generally has more than one file, for example a HTML or other base file, a CSS file, multiple images and so on. Each request for each file is one hit, so a web page with 50 images on would register 50 hits. Many years ago, hits were quoted as the main traffic metric, to amplify sites into sounding like they were receiving more traffic than they actually were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;htaccess&quot;&gt;htaccess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The .htaccess file is the default directory-level configuration file on Apache web servers. It is also known as a “distributed configuration file.” Configuration directives contained in the .htaccess file apply to the directory in which the file is placed as well as all of its subdirectories. Within the .htaccess file, settings such as authorisation and authentication, rewriting of URLs, cache control, and customised error responses can all be specified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;html&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Hypertext Markup Language) — The dominant formatting language used on the World Wide Web to publish text, images, and other elements. Invented by Tim Berners Lee in the early 1990s, HTML uses pairs of opening and closing tags (also known as elements), such as &lt;title&gt; and &lt;/title&gt;; each pair assigns meaning to the text that appears between them. HTML can be considered code, but it is not a programming language; it’s a markup language, which is a separate beast. The latest standard of HTML is HTML5, which adds powerful interactive functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;html5&quot;&gt;HTML5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upcoming, powerful standard of Hypertext Markup Language, which has added advanced
interactive features, such as allowing video to be embedded on a web page. It is gaining in popularity compared to proprietary standards, like Adobe Flash, because it is an open standard and does not require third-party plugins. Using HTML5 will allow web pages to work more like desktop applications. The latest releases of most browsers support HTML5 to varying degrees. HTML5 does not cover CSS and JavaScript, but often when people refer to HTML5, they often are using it as a blanket term, applying not only to changes to the HTML but also to changes in CSS and JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;html-tag&quot;&gt;HTML Tag&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also referred to as an HTML element, an HTML tag is the bit of code that describes how that
particular piece of the web page it is on is formatted. Typical tags specify things like headings,
paragraphs, links, and a variety of other items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;http&quot;&gt;HTTP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for HyperText Transfer Protocol. HTTP is a set of rules for transferring hypertext requests between a web browser and a web server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;https&quot;&gt;HTTPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to HTTP, HTTPS stands for HyperText Transfer Protocol over SSL (Secure Socket Layer) or, alternately, HyperText Transfer Protocol Secure. Like HTTP, it is a set of rules for transferring hypertext requests between browsers and servers, but this time it is done over a secure encrypted connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hyperlink&quot;&gt;Hyperlink&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hyperlink is a link from one web page to another, either on the same site or another one. Generally, these are text or images, and are highlighted in some way; text is often underlined or put in a different color or font weight. The inclusion of hyperlinks creates the “hyper” part of “hypertext.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypertext&quot;&gt;Hypertext&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hypertext is any computer-based text that includes hyperlinks. Hypertext can also include
presentation devices like tables or images, in addition to plain text and links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;i&quot;&gt;I&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;iframe&quot;&gt;iframe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An HTML tag that allows for one web page to be wholly included inside another; it is a popular way to create embeddable interactive features. Iframes are usually constructed via JavaScript as a way around web browsers’ security features, which try to prevent JavaScript on one page from quickly talking to JavaScript on an external page. Many security breaches have been designed using iframes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;image-map&quot;&gt;Image Map&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An image map is used in XHTML to allow different parts of an image to become different clickable elements. It can also allow some portions of an image to have no clickable element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intelligent-display&quot;&gt;Intelligent Display&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using data and consumer behavior to generate and serve a custom advertisement to a specific person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;integrated-media&quot;&gt;Integrated Media&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When multiple of the big three media types (paid, owned, and earned) overlap and work together in a marketing campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inheritance&quot;&gt;Inheritance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In CSS, elements that do not have a pre-defined style will take on the style of their parent element within the document tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inline-style&quot;&gt;Inline Style&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elements with CSS written directly around the element it affects, instead of in a separate style sheet or header style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;instagram&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A photo and video sharing social network that enables registered users to take pictures and videos via the Instagram mobile app, apply digital filters to them and then share them across other social media profiles, such as Facebook, Twitter, Tumblr, and Flickr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;infographic&quot;&gt;Infographic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An infographic (information graphic) is a graphical representation of information or data designed to be engaging and easily understandable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ip-address-internet-protocol-address&quot;&gt;IP Address (Internet Protocol Address)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A unique string of numbers that identifies each device connecting to the internet. The IP Address is your website’s home address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;j&quot;&gt;J&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Web scripting language used to enhance websites; it can make them more interactive without requiring a browser plugin. JavaScript is interpreted by your browser instead of by a web server, otherwise known as a client-side scripting language. JavaScript files generally end in .js. Despite its name, it is not related to the Java language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;joomla&quot;&gt;Joomla&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A free, open-source content management built in PHP. It is more powerful than WordPress but not as powerful as Drupal. However, it is known for its extensive design options. The name Joomla means “all together” in Swahili.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jquery&quot;&gt;jQuery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An incredibly popular open source JavaScript library designed for manipulating HTML pages and handling events. Released in 2006, jQuery quickly gained widespread adoption because of its efficiency and elegance. The definitive feature of jQuery is its support for “chaining” operations together to simplify otherwise complicated tasks. It is the most popular JavaScript library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;json-javascript-object-notation&quot;&gt;JSON (JavaScript Object-Notation)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Web data publishing format that is designed to be both easily human and machine-readable. It is an alternative to XML that is more concise because, unlike XML, it is not a markup language that requires open and close tags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;k&quot;&gt;K&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;keyvalue-store&quot;&gt;Key/value store&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simpler way of storing data than a relational or document database. Key-value stores have a
simple structure, matching values to accessible “keys,” or indices. In Web development, key/value stores are often (though not always) used for optimization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;klout&quot;&gt;Klout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A website and mobile app that uses social media analytics to rank users according to online social influence. When calculating a person’s score, Klout takes into account their activity across several social media platforms, including Twitter Facebook, LinkedIn, Google+ and Instagram. The actual relevance and accuracy of a ‘Klout Score’ has been hotly debated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;Keyword&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A keyword is a word or phrase that your audience uses to search for relevant topics on search
engines. If you are a flower shop, a relevant keyword could be “Buy Red Roses” [short keyword] or “Looking to purchase roses from a flower shop” [long tail keyword]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keyword-stuffing&quot;&gt;Keyword Stuffing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the practice of using too many keywords in content in hopes of making it more visible on search engines. You will be penalized by search engines if you resort to it. Never keyword stuff, just provide great and valuable content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;l&quot;&gt;L&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;lamp&quot;&gt;LAMP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Linux, Apache, MySQL, and PHP (or sometimes Perl or Python), and is referring to the specifications of a web server (defining the operating system, web server, database, and scripting language, in that order). One of the advantages of LAMP setups is that the software used is all free and open source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;landing-page&quot;&gt;Landing Page&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A landing page is the page where a visitor first enters a website. Often, a special landing page is created to elicit a specific action from the new visitor -usually in connection with an advertising or marketing campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;legacy-media&quot;&gt;Legacy media&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An umbrella term to describe the centralized media institutions that were dominant during the second half of the 20th century, including — but not limited to — television, radio, newspapers, and magazines, all which generally had a uni-directional distribution model. Sometimes “legacy media” is used interchangeably with “MSM,” for “Mainstream Media.” Legacy media sits in contrast with social media, where the production and sharing is of equal weight to the consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;library&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of programming, this contains code that can be accessed for software and Web
development, enabling one to perform common tasks without writing new code every time. Many libraries are freely shared. One well-known library is jQuery, released in 2006 and now the most popular JavaScript library, which boasts that it allows coders to “write less, do more.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;location-based-services&quot;&gt;Location-based services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A service, usually in a mobile Web or mobile device application, that uses your location in order to perform a certain task, such as finding nearby restaurants, giving you directions, or locating your friends. Foursquare and Gowalla are location-based services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;like&quot;&gt;“Like”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clicking ‘Like’ under something someone posts on Facebook lets them know that you enjoy it, without leaving a comment. Just like a comment though, the fact that you liked it is noted beneath the item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;linkedin&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A social networking site for professionals. Registered users may list their employment and
educational history on their profiles, connect with friends and colleagues, follow companies, join interest groups, share content and have discussions. LinkedIn is the largest professional directory of individuals and companies with over 250 million users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;live-blogging&quot;&gt;Live-Blogging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to live television or live radio, live blogging is a blog post or series of posts intended to provide real-time textual coverage of an event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;link-farm&quot;&gt;Link Farm&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A link farm is any website set up specifically to increase the link popularity of other websites by increasing the number of incoming links to that site. While some link farms are single pages listing unrelated links, others consist of networks of sites that contain multiple links back and forth to one another. Search engines can generally recognize these types of schemes and often remove link farms from their directories and penalize the sites linking to and from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;liquid-layout&quot;&gt;Liquid Layout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A liquid layout is one that is based on percentages of the browser window size. The layout of the site will change the width of the browser, even if the visitor changes their browser size while viewing the page. Liquid layouts take full advantage of the browser width a visitor is using, optimising the amount of content you can fit onscreen at one time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;m&quot;&gt;M&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;markup&quot;&gt;Markup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This refers to the coding applied to a text document to change it into an HTML, XML, or other
Markup Language document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mashup&quot;&gt;Mashup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A combination of data from multiple sources, usually through the use of APIs. An example of a
mashup would be an app that shows the locations of all the movie theaters in a particular town on a Google map. It is mashing up one data source (the addresses of movie theaters) with another data source (the geographic location of those addresses on a map).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;metadata&quot;&gt;Metadata&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data about data. Examples of metadata include descriptors indicating when information was
created, by whom and in what format. Metadata helps to organize information online and make it machine-readable. HTML is an example of metadata — it organizes the data in a web page so browsers can display it sensibly. Web pages often have hidden metadata that helps with their search engine ranks. Photos uploaded to Flickr carry metadata such as time taken, camera model and shutter speed. MP3s have metadata such as the artist name, track title, album name and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meta-tag&quot;&gt;Meta Tag&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Meta tag is an HTML tag used to include Metadata within the header of a web page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meme&quot;&gt;Meme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An image, video, piece of text or any combination of the three, typically humorous in nature, that is copied and spread rapidly by users across the internet, often starting on sites such as Reddit, and often with slight variations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;myspace&quot;&gt;MySpace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A social networking site and mobile app with a strong emphasis on music. It was the most visited social networking site in the world from 2005 until 2008 when it was overtaken by Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meetup&quot;&gt;Meetup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world’s largest network of local groups. It enables users to organise a local group or find one of the thousands already meeting up face-to-face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;micro-post-or-micro-blog&quot;&gt;Micro-Post or Micro-Blog&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A microblog is similar to a traditional blog in every way except its size. Microblogs are much smaller, sometimes comprising of nothing more than one sentence. Microposts have been made popular by social networking site Twitter, as its users are limited to posts of no more than 140 characters in length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;n&quot;&gt;N&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;net&quot;&gt;.NET&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The .NET Framework is Microsoft’s comprehensive and consistent programming model for building applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;navigation&quot;&gt;Navigation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigation refers to the system that allows visitors to a website to move around that site. Navigation is most often thought of in terms of menus, but links within pages, breadcrumbs, related links, pagination, and any other links that allow a visitor to move from one page to another are included in navigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nesting&quot;&gt;Nesting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nesting refers to putting one HTML element within another element. When this is done, the
elements have to be closed in the reverse order from how they were opened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;non-breaking-space&quot;&gt;Non-Breaking Space&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A non-breaking space, also referred to as is a white-space character that is not condensed by
HTML. The primary function of a non-breaking space is to hold open table cells or add spacing between words, or the beginning of paragraphs if an indent is desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;newsfeed&quot;&gt;Newsfeed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The homepage of most social networking sites, a news feed is a constantly updating list of stories from people and companies that a person follows on that social network. Facebook, Twitter, LinkedIn, and Instagram all use news feeds, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ning&quot;&gt;Ning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An online platform for people, businesses, and organisations to create custom social networks each with customisable appearance feel and features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;o&quot;&gt;O&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;opt-in&quot;&gt;Opt-in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process by which a user agrees to receive messages from a company. Opt-in messages,
therefore, cannot be considered as spam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;opt-out&quot;&gt;Opt-out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process by which a user elects to stop receiving messages from a company. If a user continues to receive messages after opting out these messages can be considered to be spam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-source&quot;&gt;Open Source&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open source refers to the source code of a computer program made available to the general public. Open source software includes both web-based and desktop applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open source programs are generally free or very low cost and are developed by teams of people, sometimes
comprised mostly of volunteers. PHP is a good example of open source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-graph&quot;&gt;Open Graph&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web code that determines what information (title, image, description, etc) is displayed when
someone shares a link from your website onto a social network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oauth&quot;&gt;OAuth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new method that allows users to share information stored on one site with another site. For
example, some web-based Twitter clients will use OAuth to connect to your account, instead of requiring you to provide your password directly to that third-party site. It is similar to Facebook Connect. This allows sites to validate users’ identities without having full access to their personal accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ontology&quot;&gt;Ontology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A classification system with nodes or entities, that allows non-hierarchical relationships, in contrast to a taxonomy, which is hierarchical. Taxonomies and ontologies are important in content to help related articles or topics pages. (Also see taxonomy)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-id&quot;&gt;Open ID&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open standard that lets users log in to multiple websites using the same identity through a third party. It is supported by numerous sites, including LiveJournal, Yahoo!, and WordPress. While Open ID has seen adoption among technical communities, its authentication method is not particularly intuitive, and it has not gained wide consumer acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-source-1&quot;&gt;Open source&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open source refers to a philosophy and a means of developing and licensing software and other copyrighted works so that others are free to inspect, use and adapt the original source material. There are many open source licenses. Some licenses are considered permissive (e.g. MIT and BSD), allowing inclusion in proprietary works, while others (e.g. GNU GPL) require that the resulting derivative works remain under the same license if distributed. While the term originally stemmed from software practices, the concept has now been incorporated into other fields such as medicine and agriculture. Many of the most popular technologies used in content distribution, including languages and publishing platforms, are open source. The glossary you are reading was developed using open source methodology and is available under a Creative Commons license.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;operating-system&quot;&gt;Operating system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic layer of software that controls computer hardware, allowing other applications to be built on it. The most popular operating systems today for desktop computers are the various versions of Microsoft Windows, Mac OS X, and the open-source Linux. Smartphones also have operating systems. The Palm Pre uses webOS, numerous phones use Google’s Android operating system, and the iPhone uses iOS (formerly known as iPhone OS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;online-community&quot;&gt;Online Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A virtual community consisting of people and/or businesses with common interests who use social networking sites, instant messaging apps and online forums to communicate and work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oop&quot;&gt;OOP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Object-oriented programming (OOP) is a programming paradigm that uses “objects” – data
structures consisting of data fields and methods together with their interactions – to design
applications and computer programs. Programming techniques may include features such as data abstraction, encapsulation, modularity, polymorphism, and inheritance. Many modern programming languages now support OOP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;organic-traffic&quot;&gt;Organic Traffic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is traffic that is generated to your website which is generated by a Search Engine. This could be traffic from Google, Yahoo or Bing. It’s also known as “Free” traffic. Organic traffic is the best type of traffic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;owned-media&quot;&gt;Owned Media&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything your company has direct control over the messaging on, including your website, your brochures, your call intake staff, and your social media channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;p&quot;&gt;P&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;pixel&quot;&gt;Pixel&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A contraction of picture element, a pixel refers to a single point in a graphic. Ad units are typically measured in pixels, for example, the default 468×60-sized banner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;paid-traffic&quot;&gt;Paid Traffic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paid search is when a company bids on keywords and makes advertisements around those
keywords to be displayed on search engines. These results appear separately, either on the top, bottom or right side of a search results page. Paid traffic also encompasses any form of paid advertisement that directly points to your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;page-view&quot;&gt;Page view&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A page view is a request for an entire web page document from a server by a visitor’s browser. In other words, for each page view your site had, someone (or a search engine spider) looked at that page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;perl&quot;&gt;PERL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl is a high-level, general-purpose, interpreted, dynamic programming language. Perl was originally developed by Larry Wall, a linguist working as a systems administrator for NASA, in 1987, as a general purpose UNIX scripting language to make report processing easier.
Peer-to-peer (P2P) A network architecture in which users share resources on their own computers directly with others. Often used to speed up videos and large multimedia pieces that can take a long time to download. Napster was an early example of a popular use of peer-to-peer architecture, although it was not fully peer-to-peer. Today, Skype and BitTorrent are based on peer-to-peer technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;permalink&quot;&gt;Permalink&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short for “permanent link.” Generally used only on blogs, a permalink is a link that is the permanent web address of a given blog post. Since most blogs have constantly-changing content, the permalink offers a way for readers to bookmark or link to specific posts even after those posts have moved off the home page or primary category page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;php&quot;&gt;PHP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recursive acronym for Hypertext Pre-Processor, PHP is a widely used general-purpose scripting language that is especially suited for Web development and can be embedded into HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plug-in&quot;&gt;Plug-In&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plug-in is a piece of third-party code that extends the capabilities of a website. It is most often used in conjunction with a CMS or blogging platform. Plug-ins are a way to extend the functionality of a website without having to re-write the core code of a website. Plugins can also refer to pieces of third-party software installed within a computer program to increase its functionality. The Firefox web browser has an extensive catalogue of Plugins (called ‘Addons’), which are used to extend its functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;platform&quot;&gt;Platform&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the technology world, platform refers to the hardware or software that other applications are built upon. Computing platforms include Windows PC and Macintosh. Mobile platforms include Android, iPhone and Palm’s WebOS. More recently, in an extension of its commonly used definition, Facebook has created a “platform,” allowing developers to build applications on top of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;posterous&quot;&gt;Posterous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A blogging and publishing platform to which users can submit via e-mail. Through APIs, it can push the content to other sites such as Flickr, Twitter, and YouTube. It is a for-profit company based in San Francisco that came out of the YCombinator seed start-up program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;postgresql&quot;&gt;PostgreSQL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative to MySQL, another free and open-source relational database management system on the Internet. PostgreSQL is preferred by some in the technology community for its ability to operate as a spatial database, using PostGIS extensions. This enables developers to create applications that sort information based on geography, which can mean sorting by whether various places are within a certain county or pointing out the places that are geographically closest to the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;programming-language&quot;&gt;Programming language&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A special type of language used to unambiguously instruct a computer how to perform tasks.
Programming languages are used by software developers to create applications, including those for the web, for mobile phones, and for desktop operating systems. C, C++, Objective C, Java, JavaScript, Perl, PHP, Python, and Ruby are examples of programming languages. HTML and XML are not programming languages, they are markup languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;python&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sophisticated computer language that is commonly used for Internet applications. Designed to be a very readable language, it is named after Monty Python. It first appeared in 1991 and was originally created by Guido van Rossum, a Dutch computer programmer who now works at Google. Python files generally end in .py.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pinterest&quot;&gt;Pinterest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pinboard-style photo-sharing website that allows registered users to create and manage theme-based image collections (called “boards”) such as events, interests, and hobbies. Users can “pin” content found around the web to boards they’ve created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;progressive-enhancement&quot;&gt;Progressive Enhancement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progressive enhancement is a strategy for web design that uses web technologies in a layered
fashion that allows everyone to access the basic content and functionality of a web page, using any browser or Internet connection, while also providing those with better bandwidth or more advanced browser software an enhanced version of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;property&quot;&gt;Property&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Property is a CSS term and is roughly equivalent to an HTML tag. Properties are what define how a style should appear on a given web page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pseudo-element&quot;&gt;Pseudo-Element&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pseudo-element is an element used to add a special effect to certain selectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pseudo-class&quot;&gt;Pseudo Class&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like pseudo-elements, pseudo-classes are used to add special effects to certain CSS selectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;r&quot;&gt;R&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;rwd-responsive-web-design&quot;&gt;RWD (Responsive Web Design)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a website is designed and developed to work and look good on any device, regardless of
screen size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;relational-database&quot;&gt;Relational database&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A piece of software that stores data in a series of tables, with relationships defined between them. A news story might have columns for a headline, date, text, and author, where the author points to another table containing the author’s first name, last name, and email address. Information must be structured, but this allows for powerful queries. Examples include MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL and SQLite. Most modern websites use some kind of relational database to store content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rss-really-simple-syndication&quot;&gt;RSS (Really Simple Syndication)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A standard for websites to push their content to readers through Web formats to create regular updates through a “feed reader” or “RSS Reader.” The symbol is generally an orange square with radiating white quarter circles. (Also see Atom)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;Ruby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An increasingly popular programming language known for being powerful yet easy to write with. Originally introduced in 1995 by Yukihiro “Matz” Matsumoto, Ruby has gained increasing traction since 2005 because of the Ruby on Rails development framework, which can create websites quickly. Ruby is open source and is very popular for content-based sites.
Ruby on Rails A popular Web framework based on the Ruby programming language that makes common development tasks easier “out of the box.” The power of Ruby on Rails, which was developed by the Chicago-based firm 37 Signals, comes from how quickly it can be used to create a basic website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resolution&quot;&gt;Resolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refers to the physical number of pixels displayed on a screen (such as 1280×1024). Unlike in print, display resolution does not refer to the number of pixels or dots per inch on a computer screen, as this can be changed by changing the resolution of the screen (which, of course, does not change the physical size of the screen). The resolution of an image, however, is often referred to in terms of pixels per inch, though this has very little effect on how the image is displayed on screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reddit&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A news aggregation website that is timely, interactive and personalised. Users submit links to blog posts, photos or videos and then other users vote those links up or down. The result is a list of the most engaging stories on the web at any given time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;retweet&quot;&gt;Retweet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A re-posting of someone else’s Twitter post (Tweet.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rss&quot;&gt;RSS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RSS (Rich Site Summary or Really Simple Syndication) is a content delivery vehicle. An RSS Feed uses a family of standard web feed formats to publish frequently updated information such as blog posts, news articles, photos, and videos. Web applications called RSS Readers aggregate updates from multiple RSS Feeds in one location for easy viewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;s&quot;&gt;S&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;subscriber&quot;&gt;Subscriber&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A subscriber is a person who allows a company to send him/her messages through email or other personal communication means. These subscribers are high value to publishers and businesses alike. Subscribers keep coming back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;schema&quot;&gt;Schema&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, a schema is an XML document used in place of a DTD to describe other XML documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;script&quot;&gt;Script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally refers to a portion of code on an HTML page that makes the page more dynamic and interactive. Scripts can be written in a variety of languages, including JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;selector&quot;&gt;Selector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In CSS, the selector is the item a style will be applied to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;saas-software-as-a-service&quot;&gt;SaaS (Software as a Service)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pricing strategy and business model, where companies build a software solution, usually business-to-business, and charge a fixed monthly rate to access it on the Internet. It is a type of cloud computing. Salesforce.com is the best example, but other notables include Mailchimp and even Amazon Web Services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scribd&quot;&gt;Scribd&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A document-sharing site that is often described as a “YouTube for documents” because it allows other sites to embed its content. It allows people to upload files and others to download in various formats. Recently Scribd, which is based in San Francisco, moved from Flash-based technology to HTML5 standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scripting-language&quot;&gt;Scripting language&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A programming language designed to be easy to use forevery day or administrative tasks. It may involve trade-offs such as sacrificing some performance for ease of programming. Popular scripting languages include PHP, Perl, Python, and Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;seo-search-engine-optimization&quot;&gt;SEO (Search Engine Optimization)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A suite of techniques for improving how a website ranks on search engines such as Google. SEO is often divided into “white hat” techniques, which (to simplify) try to boost ranking by improving the quality of a website, and “black hat” techniques, which try to trick search engines into thinking a page is of higher quality than it actually is. SEO can also refer to individuals and companies that offer to provide search engine optimization for websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sem-search-engine-marketing&quot;&gt;SEM (Search Engine Marketing)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A type of marketing that involves raising a company or product’s visibility in search engines by paying to have it appear in search results for a given word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;semantic-web&quot;&gt;Semantic web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vision of the web that is almost entirely machine readable, in which documents are published in languages that are designed specifically for data. It was first articulated by Tim Berners-Lee in 2001. In many implementations, tags would identify the information, such as &amp;lt;ADDRESS&amp;gt; or &lt;DATE&gt;. While there has been progress toward this front, many say this vision remains largely unrealized.&lt;/DATE&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;semantic-markup&quot;&gt;Semantic Markup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In semantic markup, content is written within XHTML tags that offer context to what the content contains. Basic semantic markup refers to using items like header and paragraph tags, though semantic markup is also being used to provide much more useful context to web pages in an effort to make the web as a whole more semantic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;server-side&quot;&gt;Server-Side&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Server-side refers to scripts run on a web server, as opposed to in a visitor’s browser. Server-side scripts often take a bit longer to run than a client-side script, as each page must reload when an action is taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sgml&quot;&gt;SGML&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Standard Generalised Markup Language. SGML is a markup language used for defining the structure of a document. SGML is not mentioned very often, but it is the markup language that serves as the basis for both XML and HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soap&quot;&gt;SOAP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Simple Object Access Protocol. SOAP is an XML-based protocol exchanging information across the internet to allow an application on one site to access an application or database on another site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;specification&quot;&gt;Specification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A specification or functional specification as it is sometimes known as a document that offers an explicit definition and requirements for a web service or technology and generally includes how the technology is meant to be used, along with the tags, elements, and any dependencies.
Social graph A mapping of the connections between people and the things they care about that could provide useful insights. The term originally promoted by Facebook and is now gaining broader usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-media&quot;&gt;Social media&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A broad term referring to the wide swath of content creation and consumption that is enabled by the many-to-many distributed infrastructure of the Internet. Unlike legacy media, where the audience is usually on the receiving end of content creation, social media generally allows three stages of interaction with content: 1) producing, 2) consuming and 3) sharing. Social media is incredibly broad and refers to blogging, wikis, video-sharing sites like YouTube, photo-sharing sites like Flickr and social networking sites like Facebook and Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;structured-thesaurus&quot;&gt;Structured thesaurus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A group of preferred terms created for editorial use to normalize and more effectively classify content. For example, the AP Stylebook is similar to (but includes more rules than) a structured thesaurus in that it gives writers preferred terms to use and standards to follow, so everyone following AP Style writes the word “website” the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sentiment-analysis&quot;&gt;Sentiment Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysing posts, comments, tweets, and messages to determine the attitude of the speaker with respect to the topic, brand or cause. The audience and messages can then be classified as either Positive, Negative or Neutral sentiment. Sentiment Analysis helps marketers to understand how people feel about their product or brand and how they are responding to campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-media-manager&quot;&gt;Social Media Manager&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The person responsible for planning and developing social media and content strategies for a brand, cause or topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-media-marketing&quot;&gt;Social Media Marketing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social Media Marketing refers to the process of gaining traffic or attention through social media networking sites, such as Facebook, Twitter, and YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-media-monitoring&quot;&gt;Social Media Monitoring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An active monitoring of social media channels for information about a company or organisation. It allows Marketing and Social Media Managers to find insights into a brands’ overall visibility on social media, measure the impact of campaigns, identify opportunities for engagement, assess competitor activity and share of voice, and be alerted to impending crises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-media-policy&quot;&gt;Social Media Policy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A corporate code of conduct that provides guidelines for employees who post content on social
media networking sites either as part of their job or as a private person. A social media policy should outline what employees are and are not allowed to say on behalf of the company, and how to respond to crises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-influencer&quot;&gt;Social Influencer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An individual who creates or shares interesting or valuable content with their niche, loyal audience of social media followers that respect and trust their opinion. Social media influencers are important to brands as they are very effective at spreading online messages, they are more trusted than brands and they are deemed more authentic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stumbleupon&quot;&gt;StumbleUpon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;StumbleUpon is an online and mobile discovery engine that finds and recommends web content to its users. Registered users list their interests and then StumbleUpon recommends content it thinks they would like. If a user likes the content they give it a thumbs up, if not, a thumbs down. StumbleUpon learns from those user actions to tailor the content it serves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snapchat&quot;&gt;SnapChat&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A photo messaging mobile app where users can take photos, record videos, add text and drawings, and send them to a controlled list of recipients. SnapChat’s USP is that messages or “snaps” self-destruct. Users set a time limit for how long recipients can view their snaps after which they will be hidden from the recipient’s device and deleted from Snapchat’s servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;skype&quot;&gt;Skype&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skype is a VOIP (voice-over-IP) and instant messaging service. Users can call, message or video conference other users for free, or can pay to call landlines and mobile phone numbers. With more than 5000 million users, Skype is the most popular communication service in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sproutsocial&quot;&gt;SproutSocial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A social media management platform that allows users and brand managers to update, post,
schedule and respond via multiple social media platforms, including; for Facebook, Twitter, and Google+. Unlike HootSuite, there is no free account option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sender-domain&quot;&gt;Sender Domain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you receive an email from info@yourcompany.com, yourcompany.com is the sender domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;t&quot;&gt;T&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tag&quot;&gt;Tag&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tag is a set of markup characters that are used around an element to indicate its start and end. Tags can also include HTML or other code to specify how that element should look or behave on the page. (See also, HTML Tag)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taxonomy&quot;&gt;Taxonomy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hierarchical classification system. In the world of content, this can be a hierarchy of terms (generally called nodes or entities) that are used to classify the category or subject content belongs to as well as terms that are included in the content. In many cases, website navigation systems appear taxonomical in that users narrow down from broad top-level categories to the granular feature they want to see. An ontology is similar to a taxonomy in that it is also a classification system with nodes or entities, but it is more complex and flexible because ontologies allow for nonhierarchical relationships. While in a taxonomy a node can be either a broader term or narrower term, in an ontology nodes can be related in any way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;template&quot;&gt;Template&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A template is a file used to create a consistent design across a website. Templates are often used in conjunction with a CMS and contain both structural information about how a site should be set up, but also stylistic information about how the site should look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transparency&quot;&gt;Transparency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of news and information, a term describing openness about information that has become increasingly popular. In many cases, it is used to refer to the transparency of government releasing data to journalists and to the public. It is often used in the context of journalists being open about their reporting process and material by sharing with their readers before the final project emerges or providing more context in addition to the final product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trending-topic&quot;&gt;Trending Topic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trending topics are those topics on Twitter being discussed more than any others. They are listed to the left of the main column and are updated in real-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tumblr&quot;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tumblr is a microblogging social networking site where registered users can post text, photos,
quotes, links, music, and videos from their web browser, mobile device, desktop or e-mail to their completely customisable Tumblr page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tweet&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A message posted using Twitter. It can be no more than 140 characters long and it can contain
links to other websites, blogs, pictures, and videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;twitter&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter is a micro-blogging social network, where registered users can post short (140 characters or less) updates, known as tweets, about what they are doing, thinking, reading, eating or many more subjects. Twitter has over 240 million monthly active users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;twitterverse&quot;&gt;Twitterverse&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also known as twitosphere or twittersphere, it is the collective postings made by Twitter users. Used to describe Twitter as an ecosystem or universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;u&quot;&gt;U&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;usability&quot;&gt;Usability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usability refers to how easy it is for a visitor to your site to use a website in its intended manner. Good usability means that elements such as navigation, content, images, and any interactive elements are easy to use, functioning the way they were intended and that any visitor will not need any special training in order to use the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ui-user-interface&quot;&gt;UI (User Interface)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The part of a software application or website that users see and interact with, which takes into
account the visual design and the structure of the program. While graphic design is an element of user interface design, it is only a portion of the consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;uri-uniform-resource-identifier&quot;&gt;URI (Uniform Resource Identifier)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way to identify the location for something on the Internet. It is most familiarly in “http:” form, but also encompasses “ftp:” or mailto:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;url-uniform-resource-locator&quot;&gt;URL (Uniform Resource Locator)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often used interchangeably with the “address” of a web page, such as http://hackshackers.com. All URLs are URIs, but not vice versa. While humans are familiar with URLs as a way to see web pages, computer programs often use URLs to pass each other machine-readable content, such as RSS feeds or Twitter information. In addition, words that appear in URLs often help boost search rankings, which is why many content sites are now shifting to URLs with headlines as opposed to data strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ux-user-experience&quot;&gt;UX (User Experience)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally referring to the area of design that involves the holistic interaction a user has with a
product or a service. It incorporates many disciplines, including engineering, graphic design, content creation, and psychology. User interface is one element of user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;url-shortener&quot;&gt;URL Shortener&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An online tool that reduces the character length of a URL (uniform resource locator) or web
address. Commonly used on social media platforms that impose character limits on users’ posts, such as Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unique-users-or-visitors&quot;&gt;Unique users or Visitors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A site’s total number of users or visitors over a certain length of time. Accuracy depends on each user logging in with a unique username to access the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unsubscribe&quot;&gt;Unsubscribe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone permanently removes themselves from your email database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;v&quot;&gt;V&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;valid&quot;&gt;Valid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valid web pages are those that return no errors based on the type of HTML/XHTML specified in the doctype declaration at the beginning of the file. The Validator checks that the code used on the web page conforms to the specifications for that version of HTML/XHTML. Web page validity can be checked through various validation services, most commonly the W3C Validator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;visit&quot;&gt;Visit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A visit is a single user coming to a website. The same visitor returning multiple times means multiple visits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;visitor&quot;&gt;Visitor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A visitor is a single user coming to a website. The same visitor returning multiple times in one day is still measured as just one visitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;viral&quot;&gt;Viral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viral, in digital terms, comes from the medial term used to describe a small infections agent that can infect all types of organisms. “Going viral” online is when a piece of content spreads just like a virus, “infecting” people when they see it by evoking emotions that spur the viewer to share it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vimeo&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vimeo is a video-sharing website on which users can upload, share and view videos. Unlike YouTube, there are no advertisements before, during or after your video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vine&quot;&gt;Vine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vine is a mobile video sharing app, owned by Twitter, Videos created with Vine have a maximum clip length of seven seconds and play on a continuous loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;w&quot;&gt;W&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-20&quot;&gt;Web 2.0&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Referring to the generation of Internet technologies that allow for interactivity and collaboration on websites. In contrast to Web 1.0 (roughly the first decade of the World Wide Web) where static content was downloaded into the browser and read, Web 2.0 uses the Internet as the platform. Technologies such as Ajax, which allow for rapid communication between the browser and the web server, underlie many Web 2.0 sites. The term was popularized by a 2004 conference, held by O’Reilly Media and MediaLive, called Web 2.0. (Also see Ajax)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-30&quot;&gt;Web 3.0&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes used to refer to the semantic web. (Also see semantic web) webOS — Operating system used on the latest generation of Palm smartphones, including the Pre and the Pixi. Apps for webOS are developed using web standards (HTML, Javascript, and CSS), which
means there is a low barrier to entry for web developers to create mobile apps for webOS as
compared to other mobile platforms. It allows for having several applications open at the same time, unlike the current iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;widget&quot;&gt;Widget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a web context, this refers to a portable application that can be embedded into a third-party site by cutting and pasting snippets of code. Common web widgets include a Twitter box that can sit on a blog or a small Google Map that sits within an invitation. Desktop widgets, such as ones offered for the Macintosh Dashboard or by Yahoo!, can be placed on the desktop of a computer, such as for weather or stocks. Similarly, Android offers the ability to add widgets to the home screens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wiki&quot;&gt;Wiki&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A website with pages that can be easily edited by visitors using their web browser, but generally now gaining acceptance as a prefix to mean “collaborative.” Ward Cunningham created the first wiki, naming it WikiWikiWeb after the Hawaiian word for “quick.” A wiki enables the audience to contribute to a knowledge base on a topic or share information within an organization, like a newsroom. The best-known wiki in existence is Wikipedia, which burst onto the scene around 2000 as one of the first examples of mass collaborative information aggregation. Other sites that have been branded “wiki” include Wikinews, Wikitravel, and WikiLeaks (which was originally but is no longer a wiki).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wordpress&quot;&gt;WordPress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most popular blogging software in use today, in large part because it is free and relatively
powerful, yet easy to use. First released by Matt Mullenweg in 2003, WordPress attracts
contributions from a large community of programmers and designers who give it additional
functionality and visual themes. Sites that use WordPress include the New York Times blogs, CNN and the LOLCats network. It has been criticized for security flaws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;xml-extensible-markup-language&quot;&gt;XML (Extensible Markup Language)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A set of rules for encoding documents and data that goes beyond HTML capacities. Whereas HTML is generally concerned with the semantic structure of documents, XML allows other information to be defined and passed such as &lt;vehicle&gt;, &lt;make&gt;, &lt;model&gt;, &lt;year&gt;, &lt;color&gt; for a car. It is the parent language of many XML-based languages such as RSS, Atom, and others. It gained further popularity with the emergence of Ajax as a way to send back data from web services, but has since lost ground to JSON, another data encoding format, which is seen as easier to work with.&lt;/color&gt;&lt;/year&gt;&lt;/model&gt;&lt;/make&gt;&lt;/vehicle&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-page&quot;&gt;Web Page&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A web page is a single document, generally written in HTML/XHTML, meant to be viewed in a web browser. In many cases, web pages also include other coding and programming (such as PHP, Ruby on Rails, or ASP). Websites are generally built from multiple interlinked web pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-server&quot;&gt;Web Server&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A web server is a computer that has software installed and networking capabilities that allow it to host websites and pages and make them available to internet users located elsewhere. There are various setups that can be used for a web server, including the LAMP setup previously mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-standards&quot;&gt;Web Standards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standards are specifications recommended by the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) for
standardising website design. The main purpose of web standards are to make it easier for both designers and those who create web browsers to make sites that will appear consistent across multiple platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;webinar&quot;&gt;Webinar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A webinar is a seminar conducted over the internet using video conferencing, instant messaging and VOIP services. Webinars are generally hosted by an organisation or company and broadcast to a select group of individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wiki-1&quot;&gt;Wiki&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wiki is a web application which allows people to add, edit, or delete content in collaboration with others, Wikipedia, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;x&quot;&gt;X&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;xhtml&quot;&gt;XHTML&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Extensible Hypertext Markup Language. Fundamentally, XHTML is HTML 4.0 that has been rewritten to comply with XML rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;xml&quot;&gt;XML&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stands for Extensible Markup Language. XML is a specification for creating other, custom markup languages. It is an extensible language because it allows for the user to define the mark-up elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compiled from the following &lt;a href=&quot;'https://www.slideshare.net/laurakerrigan/glossary-of-digital-terms'&quot;&gt;resource&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>20 Feb 2020</pubDate>
        <link>https://ideaconservatory.org/2020/02/20/digital-glossary/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ideaconservatory.org/2020/02/20/digital-glossary/</guid>
      </item>
    

    
      
        
      
    
      
        
          <item>
            <title>About</title>
            <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-idea-conservatory&quot;&gt;The Idea Conservatory&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is a personal blog where &lt;em&gt;interdisciplinary&lt;/em&gt; ideas are collected.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
            <link>https://ideaconservatory.org/about.html</link>
          </item>
        
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    

  </channel>
</rss>
